It's time for action, everybody.
행동할 시간입니다, 여러분
We've set up our colab.
콜랍을 준비했어요
Here we are, week seven, day three.
7주 차, 3일째예요
We've got our constant setup.
계속 설정해뒀어요
We've checked our model name and it's time to get into things.
모델 이름을 체크했고 get get get을 할 시간이네요.
Um, so the first thing we're going to do is log in to hugging Face, which you know, well.
첫 번째로 할 일은 얼굴 안기에 로그인하는 거예요
And then after we've logged into hugging face here, we're going to do something that you don't know
얼굴 안기 로깅에 로그인한 후에는 여러분이 잘 모르는
so well, which is new, which is logging into the wonderful weights and biases platform.
새로운 걸 할 거예요 무게와 바이어스 플랫폼에 로그인하는 거죠
So you may have already set this up as part of last week's, uh, foray into weights and biases, but
지난주에 무게와 편향성을 탐구하려고 이미 설정해 두셨을 수도 있지만 그렇지
if not, it's very simple to do.
않다면 아주 간단해요
And of course it is free.
물론 공짜고요
You go to the, uh, weights and biases W and B dot I right linked here.
무게와 편향 W와 B의 점과 I를 연결하세요
Uh, you set up a free account and then you can find your, your wand API key, your weights and biases
무료 계정을 만들면 지팡이 API 키와 무게, 편향 API 키를 찾을 수
API key.
있어요
And then you have to go to this padlock symbol here and add it in as a secret to your Google Colab.
그리고 이 자물쇠 기호로 가서 구글 Colab에 비밀리에 추가해야 해요
Um, or if you don't want to do that, you can also just type it directly into the notebook right here
그렇게 하기 싫으시면 여기 있는 공책에 직접 입력하셔도
instead as well.
돼요
But it's recommended to use the secrets.
하지만 비밀을 사용하는 걸 추천해요
So once you've set up weights and biases on we go.
무게와 편향을 설정하면 시작할게요
We then load in the data set, and we can just quickly check that the data set is what we expect.
그런 다음 데이터 세트를 로드하고 데이터 집합이 우리가 기대하는 건지 재빨리 확인할 수 있어요
We expect there to be and we expect.
그럴 거라고 예상하고 기대하죠
Let's have a look at how many training data points we're looking for 400,000 of them there they are
훈련 데이터 포인트가 얼마나 많은지 봅시다 400,000개를 찾고 있어요 400,000개의
400,000 training data points a lot of them.
훈련 데이터 포인트죠 아주 많아요
Let's look at the first one.
첫 번째를 보죠
Just make sure it's exactly what we expect it should be.
우리가 예상하는 대로 만들어 주세요
The text in this training data point is the prompt we're expecting followed by the price right here.
이 훈련 데이터 포인트의 텍스트는 우리가 기대하는 프롬프트입니다 그리고 여기 가격이 있죠
And it's going to be this that the model is going to be desperate to predict this next token and get
모델은 필사적으로 다음 토큰을 예측하고 get을 할
it right.
거예요
And we also have the actual price here.
실제 가격도 나와 있어요
You can see we're rounding it to the nearest whole token.
가장 가까운 토큰으로 가는 게 보이죠
And we tell it that we're looking.
우리가 찾는다고 말하는 거죠
How much does this cost to the nearest dollar, the nearest token the nearest dollar.
가장 가까운 1달러의 비용은 얼마일까요? 가장 가까운 1달러의 토큰은 얼마일까요?
And there is the price.
대가가 따르죠
The real price.
진짜 가격요
If we look at the test data set and not that we'll be using that today.
테스트 데이터 세트를 보면∙∙∙ 오늘 그걸 사용하진 않을 거예요
But you will remember the test data set is very similar.
하지만 테스트 데이터 세트도 아주 유사하다는 걸 기억하실 거예요
Just one tiny difference.
아주 작은 차이죠
There is not a price after here.
이다음에는 가격도 없어요
It just says price is dollar.
가격은 달러라고만 쓰여 있어요
And that's that is what we're training our model to be good at doing.
그런 걸 잘하도록 모델을 훈련하고 있어요
Okay.
네
So um, if we're logged in, if we're asking to log to weights and biases, it then sets up the weights
저희가 로그인해서 무게와 바이어스에 로그인하도록 요청하면 무게와 바이어스 프로젝트를
and Biases project.
설정해요
This is in fact not required to have this line of code, because actually hugging face will do this
이 코드는 사실 이 줄이 있을 필요가 없어요 왜냐하면 얼굴을 안으면 이렇게 되거든요 만약
for you if you start to run and you don't, you haven't run this line.
실행을 시작했는데 이 줄을 실행하지 않았다면요
But I sometimes add this because you can also, if you wish, pass in a config config a config with
하지만 가끔 이걸 추가해요 원한다면 매개 변수로 구성된 구성을 통과시킬 수도
some parameters, and that lets you set up some extra um, attributes that will appear in weights and
있거든요 그럼 무게나 편향에 나타날 추가 특성을 설정할 수 있죠
That's a useful trick to know.
유용한 정보네요
Um, but but anyways, you can run this or not.
어쨌든 이걸 실행하든 말든 맘대로 해요
It doesn't make much difference.
그게 그거죠
Okay, so then this we saw before.
네, 이건 아까 봤죠
We're just going to take this hyper parameter and decide whether we're going to use the bits and bytes
이 하이퍼 매개 변수를 가지고 4비트 수량화를 위해 비트 및 바이트 구성을 쓸지
config for four bit quantization or for eight bit.
8비트 사용할지 결정하는 거죠
And we are of course going with four bits.
물론 50센트짜리로 할게요
We're going all the way down.
계속 내려갈 거예요
And then it is time to load in the tokenizer and the model.
이제 토큰라이저와 모델을 로드할 차례예요
And so usual code to load the tokenizer.
토큰마이저를 로드하는 일반적인 코드죠
I mentioned to you that this is boilerplate stuff that you do that tells the trainer that we want to
이것은 상용적인 것이라고 말씀드렸었는데요 트레이너에게 모든 데이터
pad every data point so that it fills up our maximum sequence length, and it should pad it all up with
포인트를 패드하고 싶다고 말합니다 최대 시퀀스 길이를 채우기 위해서요 그리고 문장 끝
end of sentence tokens just to fill up that that set of characters, the 182, uh, length of our of
토큰들로 모든 것을 패드해야 합니다 글자 집합을 채우기 위해서요 시퀀스에서 토큰의 182개
our tokens in our, in our sequences.
길이 말이죠
So we'll pad them to the right with these tokens.
이 토큰으로 오른쪽에 패드하죠
And then there's this one line here, which is just another boilerplate thing to set the pad token ID
그리고 여기 이 라인이 있는데요 이것은 또 다른 표준 문항으로 패드 토큰 ID를 생성 환경
on this thing called the generation config.
설정하는 것인데요
And the reason that put this in there is it stops it saying a warning later that it that it doesn't
이걸 저기에 넣은 이유는 나중에 경고를 막기 위해서예요 이걸 보지 않는다는
see this, but I actually think it would take this anyway.
경고요 하지만 어쨌든 이걸 받을 것 같아요
So so this avoids it printing an unnecessary warning.
그래서 이건 불필요한 경고를 인쇄하는 걸 피하죠
Um, and then we end by printing the memory footprint as usual, and we see that it is the 5.6GB that
마지막으로 메모리 발자국 프린팅으로 마무리합니다 5가 보이죠 4 비트 버전의 라마는 6GB가
we expect for our four bit version of the llama, 3.18 billion parameter model.
예상됩니다, 3이죠 180억 매개 변수 모델이죠
Okay, one more technicality here.
세부 사항이 하나 더 있어요
This thing called the data collator.
데이터 합성기라는 거예요
So there is this, um, this cunning thing that when we're doing our training, we're going to be passing
이런 교묘한 방법이 있어요 훈련을 할 때 가격을 포함한 전체 배열을 통과시키면
in the the full sequence, including the price, and the model will see lots of examples of this and
모델에서 많은 예시를 볼 수 있고 이런 토큰을 예측하는 능력이 점점
get better and better at predicting these tokens.
좋아지죠 get it
But there's a bit of a catch.
하지만 비트가 있죠
We actually don't care for the model to learn about how to predict all of the tokens in the prompt up
사실 우린 달러 기호가 나올 때까지 모든 토큰을 예측하는 모델에
until the dollar sign.
관심 없어요
We want it to learn how to predict that token right there.
여기 있는 토큰을 예측하는 법을 배우게 하는 거죠
So we don't want it to spend lots of time seeing how good it is at writing descriptions of products,
그래서 제품 설명을 얼마나 잘하는지 확인하느라 많은 시간을 들이지 않고
and then also learn the price we want it to focus on that price.
그 가격에 집중할 수 있는 가격을 알아내길 원하죠
Um, and, and doing that involves setting up something called a mask.
그러려면 마스크라는 걸 만들어야 해요
When you tell the trainer that you don't need it to learn about the prompt, you just want it to take
트레이너에게 프롬프트에 대해 배울 필요가 없다고 할 때 컨텍스트를 주기 위해
this into account, to give it context.
이걸 고려하길 원하죠
But learn how to predict this token right here after the dollar sign.
하지만 달러 기호 다음에 나오는 토큰을 예측하는 법을 배우세요
Setting up masks is a bit fiddly and involves a bit of uh um uh, yeah, yeah, a bit of, uh, messing
마스크를 세팅하는 건 손이 많이 가고 네, 토큰으로 비트를 만들어야
around with with tokens.
해요
But luckily hugging face has made it very easy indeed with a nice little utility that does it all for
다행히도 안아주는 얼굴 덕분에 아주 쉬워졌습니다 모든 걸 대신 해주는 작고 실용적인 장치가
you.
있죠
And it's called the data Collator for completion only.
데이터 컬레이터라고 부르는데 오직 완성만을 위한 거죠
LM, uh, which is what we've got.
LM, 그게 우리예요
We've got something where all we want to do is have it complete.
이제 완성만 하면 되는 거예요
This particular sentence.
이 문장요
How it works is you come up with something that's called the response template, which sounds very fancy,
응답 템플릿이라는 걸 만들어내는 겁니다 아주 거창하게 들리지만 그냥 다음에
but it just simply means what is the chunk of text which is going to indicate that I want you to predict
뭐가 올지 예측하라는 걸 나타내는 텍스트 덩어리가 무엇인지를 의미하죠
And in our case, it is quite simply price is dollar sign.
이 경우엔 간단히 가격은 $s 사인이죠
We want it to predict the next thing after that.
그 다음 일을 예측하게 하고 싶어요
So you put that into something called response templates and then you create something, an instance
응답 템플릿에 넣고 뭔가를 만드는 거죠 데이터 콜렛터의 완성을
of data collator for completion, only passing in the response templates.
위한 인스턴스요 응답 템플릿에만 전달하는 거죠
And you also have to tell it your tokenizer, and it will use that to build the final set of masked
토큰라이저라고 알려줘야 해요 그럼 그걸 이용해 트레이너로 가는 마스크된
data that goes into the the trainer.
데이터 최종 세트를 빌드하죠
And you'll see that in just a second.
잠시 후에 보실 수 있어요
So this is super simple and it's doing something quite sophisticated behind the scenes and making it
이건 아주 간단해요 막후에서 아주 정교한 작업을 하고 있죠 우릴
easy for us.
쉽게 해줘요
All right.
좋아요
And finally the last the last big moment for us.
드디어 마지막 중요한 순간이에요
This is going to look like lots of code, but it's not actually that much to it.
많은 코드처럼 보이지만 사실 그렇게 많지는 않아요
We are about to call our trainer, and we're going to have to pass in two sets of parameters.
트레이너를 부를 거예요 두 개의 매개 변수를 통과시켜야 해요
One of them is called the Laura config.
그중 하나는 로라 구성이에요
It's the hyperparameters that relate to how we're doing our Laura training.
hyperperameter는 로라 훈련과 관련이 있어요
And the other, the psft config is the supervised fine tuning.
다른 하나는 감독하에 미세한 조율을 하는 거죠
Config is just general stuff about how training should work, and what I've done is I've basically set
구성이란 훈련이 어떻게 작동해야 하는지에 대한 일반적인 거죠 제가 한 건 기본적으로 이런 것들을 노트북
these things up to pull from the constants that we defined right at the top of the notebook, like alpha
상단에 정의한 상수에서 끌어오기 위해 설정했어요 알파나 드롭 아웃 같은
and dropout, and then the things that don't matter so much, I've just put put in here what to use.
거요 그리고 별로 중요하지 않은 건 사용할 걸 여기 적어뒀어요
And these are not important hyperparameters or they're or they're just things where we should set it
이건 중요한 hyperperameter가 아니에요 그냥 특정
to a to a certain value.
값에 설정해야 하는 거죠
So you can see that for the Laura parameters, we of course pass in the alpha, which we know well,
로라 매개 변수에 대해 보다시피 알파를 넘깁니다 잘 아는 거죠 다시
I won't define it yet again, the dropout and the target modules that we're targeting.
정의하진 않을게요 우리가 대상으로 하는 드롭아웃과 대상 모듈이요
So so that goes into the Laura config, the training parameters, the SFT config had stuff like the
그래서 로라 구성과 훈련 매개 변수 SFT 구성에는 실행 이름 같은 게 있어요
How many epochs are we running the batch size?
몇 개의 편성에서 작업하죠?
Uh, super important 16.
아주 중요한 16살요
In my case, it might be one for you if you're on a on a the T4 box.
제 경우에는 T4 박스에 있다면 그럴 수도 있겠네요
Uh, the gradient accumulation, that is one for us.
그러데이션이 쌓이는 게 문제네요
And then things like learning rate the cosine scheduler that we decided to use.
그리고 우리가 사용하기로 한 코사인 스케줄러의 학습률 같은 것도요
Um, and then just down at the bottom here, we're saying that we want this to be pushing to the hub.
그리고 여기 아래쪽에 허브에 푸시하는 걸 원한다고 돼 있어요
Um, every time that, that it's doing a save, which is every 5000 of the, of the batch steps, we
저장할 때마다 즉, 배치 단계 5000개마다 이 모델을 허브에 푸시해야
want it to push this model to the hub so that we'll get a series of saves to the hub.
합니다 그래야 허브에 일련의 저장량을 얻을 수 있죠
And we can see our model at each of those points.
각각의 지점에서 모델을 볼 수 있어요
Um, and we ask to give it this name, and we say we want it to be a private, uh, repo so that it's
그리고 이 이름을 부여하고 개인의 압류로 하고 싶다고 했어요 좋은 결과를
not public yet until we're satisfied that we've got great results from it.
얻을 때까지 아직 공개하지 않게요
Uh, and then this is the final line.
이게 마지막 선이에요
We set up something called an SFT trainer.
특수 훈련 교관이라는 걸 만들었어요
We pass in just a few simple things.
간단한 것만 몇 개 통과하죠
Number one, it needs to know the base model.
첫째, 기본 모델을 알아야 해요
What is the underlying model that we want to fine tune, which is llama 3.1.
섬세하게 조정해야 하는 기본 모델은 llama 3이죠 1번요
Number two what is our training data?
2번, 훈련 데이터는요?
We pass that in.
그걸 전달해요
What are the Lora parameters.
로라의 조건은요?
This has as you know it has the alpha, the r, the dropout, the tokenizer, the training parameters
아시다시피 알파, r, 드롭아웃 토큰라이저도 있고 방금 설정한 훈련 매개
that we just set up right here.
변수도 있어요
And finally we pass in that collator, which is that sneaky object which knows to look for the prices
마지막으로 콜레이터를 통과시킵니다 교활한 객체죠 가격의 $ 기호를 찾아서
dollar sign and it's telling it.
알려주는 거예요
Don't bother predicting what comes before that.
그 전은 예측하지 마세요
Worry about what comes next.
다음을 걱정하세요
Um, and so this then will have set up our trainer.
이건 트레이너를 설정하는 거고요
And in the next video we'll run this single line fine tuning train, which is the line that kicks it
다음 영상에서는 이 선 하나로 미세 튜닝 트레인을 작동시킬 거예요 이 선이 시작이죠
Uh, that will be quite the moment.
멋진 순간이 될 거예요
So without further ado, let's go do that.
그럼 지체 없이 그걸 하러 가죠